<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of advice concerning marriage by A.B.</title>
            <author>A. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18344</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12729417</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12729417</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66410</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27103)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66410)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 374:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of advice concerning marriage by A.B.</title>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Miller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. 29-[30].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Princeton University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66410:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66410:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER OF ADVICE Concerning Marriage.</p>
            <p>By <hi>A. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Miller</hi> at the Gilded Acorn in St <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, near the little North-Door. MDCLXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:66410:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap> Opinion have rendred them unfit or unſeemly for Huſbands, are yet for Wives not only decent but commendable; and to common welfare ſo neceſſary, that the neglect of them is ſeldom without decay: Hence that thred-bare ſaying, <hi>If you will thrive, look how you wive.</hi> In which ſingle reſpect, the very ſloth and incapacity of moſt women now-adays (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Heirs and Fondlings, bred even to a contempt of Huſwifery) is without profuſeneſs a defect ſcarce to be repair'd by fortune. Wherefore to one that hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a ſolid Eſtate, not to be acquir'd, but well managed &amp; gradually improv'd, 'tis certainly upon this account more profitable to purchaſe the Wife, whoſe thrift is it ſelf a yearly, nay weekly revenue; than for one to compaſs a lump of Money with an exceſſive Rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge atending it: But if to ſuch defect ſhould be added the affectation of our preſent Court and City<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomp (and what better can be there expected?) no Bank confines ſuch a Torrent, nor can any Pile of wealth afford Fewel for ſuch a Flame; the quantity ſerving only to accelerate the Conſumption.</p>
            <p>For doubtleſs to that Sex an Expence belongs, which though never ſo demurely carried, far exceeds that of Men; but meeting with Quality and Vanity, knows no meaſure. Maids, I confeſs, acting purely for themſelves, and for the moſt part making a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Neceſſity, may perhaps with their ſingular affected Parſimony, with other notable ſhifts, ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and palliate this expenſive humour: inded it is their Maſter-piece ſo to do. But then in the change of their condition (and withal concernment, it ſhould ſeem, by Marriage) like an unnatural reſtraint, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out extraordinary diſcretion and kindneſs to their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66410:2"/> Huſbands, it breaks forth with double violence: their Train is much longer, their Viſits and Collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more ſumptuous and frequent, their Dreſſes more curious and elaborate than ours; their Journeys in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely cumberſome and expenſive: Not to mention there Childbeds and Goſſipping, to the due equipage whereof all Trades muſt conſpire: yet where are the men that conſider this? Can we then expect it from Women? Their partiality is ſuch, that though they cauſe double the Charge, yet if they bring but half the Eſtate, they reckon, that as purchaſers they have right to ſpend: a prejudice with our Gallants ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, but withal dangerous, that were it duly weighed, it would ſtrike at the very root of Marriage. Suitors therefore we ſee are obliged by no means to conſult their Reaſon, much leſs their Arithmetick; Ignorance may well be ſtyled the Mother of their Devotion.</p>
            <p>Howbeit I would not be conſtrued herein to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt Marriage: one may I hope blame the Corruptions of Lawyers without irreverence to the Law. Error is but a Foil to Truth, and by redreſſing abuſes, the regular uſe is beſt eſtabliſh'd. Marriage we know is a ſtate neceſſary both to the Conſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Comfort of Mankind, conſecrated by God himſelf, who would never have inſtituted and ſo recommended it, were it not moſt conſiſtent with our well-being; but the beſt perverted, proves the worſt: and in nothing hath there been a greater departure from primitive intention than in Marriage, to the bane and ſcandal of Society.</p>
            <p>The root of this, as of all other evils, is Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but by the fate of irregular Appetites ſo dazled, that it ſhoots at random very wide of the mark. To
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66410:3"/> ſuch as obſerve the ſhrewdneſs of Covetous men in all other purſuits, it may ſeem a miracle, that herein they ſhould act with ſo little foreſight; and might perhaps be referred to divine Juſtice, thus arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ill-gotten Eſtates. But alas, their Example, with the fame they carry for wiſdom, hath miſguided perſons of better Principles; whom to reclaim were methinks a publick ſervice: Wherefore leaving thoſe to their incorrigible vice and deluſion, I frame my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to you, who may communicate it to ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Gentlemen of your acquaintance, where you judge it needful or uſeful.</p>
            <p>Our Gentry may now be conſidered under four Conditions or Capacities; <hi>viz.</hi> Such as have little or nothing to truſt to; ſuch as have bare Competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; ſuch as have fair Eſtates, but encumbred or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectant; and ſuch as have ample and clear For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
            <p>How needleſs it is for the firſt of theſe to marry needs no proof; yet if ſome favourable opportunity ſhould tempt them ſo to endeavour the improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their condition, which they can hardly much impair, they are partly excuſable: only let them not too much triumph in their purchaſe, nor be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed if they mend not by their change of Climate, for ſome that have tried will inform them, there is no Villainage to the Apron-tenure. If in any caſe ſuch Matches have ſucceſs, 'tis with Cadets of the Nobility, whoſe high Birth ſerves to ballance the Wealth, and bridle the arrogance of women.</p>
            <p>The ſecond rate of Gentlemen in former times were obſerved frequently to advance their Eſtates by Marriage; but it was in the Golden age of Female-innocence,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66410:3"/> ere they had taſted the Tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; whilſt their Breeding was ſtrict, their Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites regular, their Wills governable, and even Heirs were not therefore the worſe Wives: The Scene is dangerouſly altered; thoſe Pleaſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> boats now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days carrying ſuch Sail, as without skilful and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Steerage muſt needs overſet in our Seas. Hence with Gentlemen of indifferent Eſtates, when they go a Fortune-catching, it commonly fares as with the Dog in the Fable; their prizes in the upſhot proving worſe to them than Blanks: our Politicians therefore recommend to them Marriage Alamode; Yet not to flatter the Vice and Prejudice of the Age, I dare maintain, That prudent Wedlock is even for ſuch the more thriving ſtate, and no ſuch Bugbear as ſome of our Wits repreſent it; there being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances enough of our beſt Gentry with moderate Eſtates, both living honourably &amp; providing well for Poſterity: and nothing now more familiar than to ſee ſome rich with 500 <hi>l.</hi> a year, to the envy and reproach of others that are poor with their Thouſands: For as Citizens ſay of their Shops, <hi>Home ſeldom fails to keep thoſe that keep home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Gentlemen of the Third Rank, <hi>viz.</hi> whoſe Eſtates are expectant or incumbred, 'tis indeed more expedient to marry for Riches, yet is not ſuch obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion equal to all; neither indeed ſeems it requiſite but in particular caſes, where diſcretion perhaps would rather dictate the preferring of ſingle Life, or at leaſt the deferring of Marriage; for Inſtance; If to a certain fair expectance there be for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent only a bare penſion.</p>
            <p>I know it is a Maxim authoriſed by current pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66410:4"/> That encumbred Eſtates are beſt cleared with Marriage-portions; but it proves a treacherous Cure, neither indeed is it a proper expedient: For if the Eſtate be great and the Encumbrance comparatively ſmall, an eaſie ſale would beſt diſcharge it, leaving the Patrimony ſound and the Owner free. And one who having thus ſettled his Affairs, and afterwards weds to his beſt Choice, ſhall ſooner thrive and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe than the moſt proſperous Fortune-catcher. But if the Debt be a dangerous Sum, the payment of it by Marriage is next to deſperate; it faring with ſuch Adventurers as with Privateers, who, betwixt the charge of Rigging, hazard of miſſing and triumph of getting Booties are in all Events deſtined to be Bankrupts. Like cold Drink in a Fever, it cools the mouth, but inflames the blood; and at beſt helps no otherwiſe to patch up an encumbred and declining Condition, than doth an outward Prop to ſupport a crazie Building. Much might however be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in excuſe for thoſe, whoſe exigencies ſo ſtimulate and perplex them, that they neither freely act nor clearly judge; whereas our Gentlemen of large and entire Eſtates, when they wrack upon that Coaſt, are purely to thank themſelves.</p>
            <p>You will tell me, Marriage now lies under great obloquy, as a Phlegmatick ſtate of Life, yielding no variety but of trouble; fit only for the blew or Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern-apron, but uneaſie for men of generous Minds and free Fortunes, preſumed not to brook ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of their Converſations and Appetites: 'Tis repreſented as the Purgatory of Perſons and Canker of Eſtates; nay, the Rules of the King's Bench (if ſome of our Wits may be credited) have more El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow-rom:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66410:4"/> for oft methinks it proves ſo, the greater their reproach, who ſo fondly abandon their true intereſt, and diſparage it; there being certainly no real inconvenience which well-adviſed Marriage impoſes, no honeſt freedom which it denies to men of plentiful Eſtates; rather many advantages pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to it, it being their great Prerogative, that their Choice is in effect unconfin'd: For we daily ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the owner of a fair and plentiful Revenue, diſpenſing but with Portion, needs not deſpair of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs almoſt in any other purſuit; and 'tis no leſs certain, that to perſons of ſuch Fortune Portions are ſuperfluous.</p>
            <p>The moſt common and plauſible excuſe of our ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble Matches, is the ſame Scare-crow which frights ſo many from marrying at all, forſooth, the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of being over-charged with Children, to the clogging of their Eſtates, or at leaſt abridging of their Pomp: A conſideration at beſt otherwiſe: For ſince by ſingular Providence, even Families of ordinary Rank and Eſtate, in ſtead of being bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened, are notably ſupported by numerous Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. How ſecure from that danger muſt our eminent Landlords be! rather what Latitude have they for Bounty, with allowance for ſome Vanity!</p>
            <p>But there is one miſtake common to great Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords and great Princes, or rather Parallel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. Great<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Princes were ever noted to place all their Glory in Conqueſt, ſuppoſing, that if with infinite Charge and Hazard, to the oppreſſion of their ſubjects and neighbours, they added one little Province of their own acquiring to their vaſt Dominions and Titles, they gave a ſufficient account
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66410:5"/> of their Sceptres: Whereas they then purſue the real Intereſt of Empire, when by due execution of good Laws, and careful obedience of their People, they govern more ſecurely, nay, more abſolutely than the Sultan doth with his Scemitar; rendring ſmall Territories equivalent to Monarchies. With like prejudice great Landlords, even thoſe that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the fame of Wiſdom, amuſe and perplex them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in purſuit of ſomewhat to be acquired by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage or purchaſe, no doubt as a Trophy of their good conduct; forſaking in the mean time their more noble and ſolid advantage, which conſiſts in the generous Fruition and gradual Improvement of what they already poſſeſs. 'Tis one of the ſoreſt evils under the Sun, the very Canker of wealth, like the Worm in the Gourd, that one already ſeized of a vaſt eſtate (more perhaps than he hath heart to uſe or Brain to manage) ſhould haraſs or but diſeaſe himſelf in the acqueſt of ſome little acceſſion: more brutiſh herein than Beaſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who being in rich Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, break no Fences, nor look any further. How happy were it, could ſuch but be acquainted with the goodly privileges and improvements of their Eſtates by diſcreet enjoyment; ſo at leaſt, as not to ſeek what they have, and dearly buy, or rather ſell and betray their own Fortunes! To ſee a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Eſtate, out of the Uſurer's reach, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out colour of Exigence, not raſhly, but induſtriouſly and with great oſtentation of wiſdom, for ſorry pelf and lucre, expoſe himſelf, with all his hopes and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, to the venture (indeed certain miſchief) of an unworthy Match; what is it but to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orn'd to his own manifeſt wrong, and hired as it were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66410:5"/> to deſtroy himſelf? ſuch errour being every way ſurrounded with repentance.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, 'tis an authentick Obſervation, That great Portions are commonly attended with great diſappointments and frauds; however, that Land is rarely therewith purchaſed or Eſtates im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, almoſt as ſeldom as with Moneys won at play; they ſerving for the moſt part rather like Sawces to humour the palate and whet the appetite, than food to nouriſh; dangerous Fewel, and Decoys of vanity and expence. I grant that ſuch as have little or no other fund oft-times ſpeed better with them; partly by reaſon of the thrift to which they have been obliged, little being from ſuch expected; chiefly for that great kindneſs on the Womans ſide, being the ground-work of ſuch Matches, diſpoſes them to chearful compliance: Much like Offices and Court-employments, which though commodious for Cadets, yet with great Landlords we find ſcarce turn to account. When the Bills of Wooing, Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and Honey-year are deſraid, the Baſte I doubt proves more than the Roaſt.</p>
            <p>Yet in purſuit thereof, the Fortune<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> catcher diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims all thoſe nobler Conſiderations and Attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives, moſt of which are ſingly without compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be preferr'd, but ſome ineſtimable, for that by Nature, Precept or Example they are propagated, (<hi>viz.</hi>) lovely Feature and Shape, graceful Motion, ſound Conſtitution, Gayety of Humour, Quickneſs of Wit, diſcreet Behaviour, approved Huſwifery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In lieu whereof he oft-times both ſtifles his Affections and buries his Family, by marrying certain Barrenneſs or Infirmity, courting imperfections which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66410:6"/> carry with them an Attainder of Blood. At beſt, he blindly ſubjects even his preſent Fortune to the diſcretion of a woman taken at random from the Lottery of a licentious Age. For with what Arms ſhall he defend himſelf from her Wantonneſs, Malice, or but Folly? Some indeed oppoſe the Huſband's Authority as a ſufficient Target; but alas! our Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, I doubt may now afford a full Regiment of ſuch Martyrs: ſo dangerous a Privilege hath it prov'd of late for our fair Ladies to be unconcern'd in Debts of their own contracting, and ſo make their Huſband's <hi>Mittimus</hi> at their pleaſure. Stay, there is yet (if poſſible) a ſharper Sting in the tayl of this Miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; for to win thoſe unprofitable Trophies, vaſt Joyntures, and even Liquid Rents are often extorted, Conveyances and Truſts are multiplied to dangerous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Expence, but far more dangerous Encumbrance; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the endleſs perplexing of Claims and Titles, a fruitful S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dolet of pernicious Suits and Diſcords in after<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> times. Troth, if the Huſband henceforth write <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> 'tis all he can hope for: She reckons his Eſtate her Purchaſe, and diſputes his Property; not to lie admoniſh'd without Sullenneſs, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troll'd without the menace of a final Breach, and intimation of worſe, the danger of Elopment being fairly provided for by ſutable Alimony of courſe preſum'd: towards which, and for the perfect bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of fooliſh Jealouſie to its good behaviour, on the ſame worthy Conſideration whole Patrimonies are likewiſe ſettled; whereby at one daſh the ſheepiſh Owner, forfeiting as it were his Inheritance becomes a ſorry Penſioner, deveſted of all Authority, unable to ſerve his Prince or Friend, or help himſelf in caſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66410:6"/> of any Exigent unforeſeen. His eldeſt Son he makes his Landlord of an intereſt wholly forreign and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent, able to borrow more pounds than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf can fairly ſhillings; and claiming not by deſcent, much leſs by his Father's bounty, but by even his own or his Mothers purchaſe, or at leaſt the wiſe proviſion of his Parents on that ſide. No marvel then if his Obedience prove anſwerable, ſince with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome preternatural Obligation, 'tis daily ſeen what becomes of filial Duty and Reverence. His younger Children, like Eſtrich's Eggs, he expoſes to pity, that is, contempt, and the miſeries that attend poverty and quality in conjunction; oft-times diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling himſelf ſo much as to countenance them in a Mechanick Courſe, with ſuch manifeſt hardſhip, that he can never look clearly on them, nor almoſt chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge their obſervance. Thus it happens to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, as where Dung lies ſtill unſpread; the whole Farm is Barren, and the Maxine noiſom. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, to me methinks it is not a little ſtrange, that in the very Bargain ſuch Fallacies ſhould be obtruded on men endued with Number and Senſe. Firſt the Portion is computed to yield an Income anſwerable to the Current Rate of Intereſt, and meaſures for Settlement accordingly taken; whereas, though it came clearly to account (as ſcarce ever it doth) yet with Gentlemen of noble and free Eſtate, whoſe ſtock ſeldom runs in that Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, 'tis fair if it turn to half that profit; and then 'tis admitted as a Revenue proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the preſent Maintenance and Port of Wives: when, alas, were it fairly examined, not groſly ſwallowed like a Dutch Reckoning <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>meale,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:66410:7"/> it would but too plainly appear, the Pomp of ſuch Women is rarely defrayed at double the charge: For ſo great is their overweening, ſo little their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs or Juſtice to their Huſbands (into whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies they are not kindly engraffed) that thoſe who at their Parents allowance were proud enough of keeping their Maid, and gloried in the Managery of a ſorry Stipend, do, on their Marriage, even chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge an exorbitant Train and boundleſs Expence, little caring what becomes of their Huſbands, ſo they hold faſt their Joyntures.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, a generous and prudent match, is further improved with divers Felicities naturally attending it; which I ſhall endeavour by way of <hi>Antitheſis</hi> to exemplifie in many pregnant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>To thoſe golden Idols of courſe belongs a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious worſhip, with ſuch tedious and frivolous addreſſes and purſuit for the moſt part, as, beſides the preſent Exceſs, lays a foundation for future un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrift, (a Torrent which is ſcarce to be ſuddenly check'd;) ſo driving men upon all accounts to a ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy After-game. For though the Oaths of Suitors are become a By-word (as for their Vanity they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) yet at beſt they are dangerous impertinencies, ſcarce conſiſtent with Wiſdom or Honour. To vow a Talent with meaning a Drachme, to flatter egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly without ground of Truth, how vile and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is it! And if ſuch as uſe it meet with the ſucceſs they merit, by being taken at their words, are they not paid in their own Coyn? For how can they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily aſſert that Authority which they have ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated? And with what Forehead can they chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66410:7"/> that Duty, where they have ſworn ſuch Fealty and done ſuch Homage? He at once cuts off all this Pageantry, who appay'd in his Self-ſufficiency with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other regard, gratifies his inclinations, makes his own Conditions, and is courted to his real advantage: he breaks not his word, in keeping and uſing his power, nor renders himſelf Uſurper to his own Right; but finds her indeed a Wife whom he never made a Miſtreſs, nor furniſh'd with any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of aſpiring to it. How little ſoever ſhe brings, I dare profeſs, that at ſeven years end, on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, he ſhall boaſt of his Bargain.</p>
            <p>It hath been noted as the fatal Error of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Oeconomy to begin at the wrong end, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulging preſent Exceſs, and projecting future Thrift: We ſee goodly Veſſels daily ſplit upon that Rock; where at none will marvel that conſider how prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous and almoſt impracticable it is, from the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of playing the After-game of Fortune and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming evil (but eſpecially voluptuous) Habits; from the daily growing charge of Children and their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, as alſo from the diſrepute attending ſuch Retrenchments. Beſides, of what conſequence in it ſelf conſidered muſt it be to ſave or ſpend at firſt? Since a ſtock timely ſaved, may by eaſie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement in ſome years double its Capital; but a Sum early borrowed ſhall within the ſame pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod quadruple its Debt: whereby the perpetual plenty or penury of Families, with all the enſuing benefits or miſchiefs ſeem chiefly hereon to depend. Hence that homely but uſeful Proverb, of taking her down in her Wedding-ſhooes; which to Wives not intoxicated with Fortune is familiar enough: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66410:8"/> thoſe Courting ſtocks, from the Cradle cockered, and only wedded to their Wills, are not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced but by late Experience, the curſt School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtreſs of Fools.</p>
            <p>No man is ſo unvers'd in houſhold or worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, but muſt obſerve how good Families are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and both intereſt and repute advanced by the honourable Reſidence of Landlords upon their Demeſnes, by conſtant abſence or frequent motion undermin'd and eclipſed: Inſomuch as ſome ſtick not to averr, that before the common uſe of Coaches, few but Traytors or Felons made ſhipwrack of their Freeholds. Indeed if the Huſband ſhould be forth by occaſions or on publick Service, yet what hath the Wife to do, but ſtay at home, and as a truſty Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty act for his intereſt by his order in his ſtead? Her Houſe is her proper Sphere, her beſt Title that of Huſwifery; which if ſhe merit not, ſhe is ſo far from being a help meet for him, as ſhe is certainly his great encumbrance. But is this the practice of our Female-ſparks? are theſe the Maxims of ſuch as by the falſe meaſures, and with the natural arrogance of rich Wives, ever fancy they have over-bought their Huſbands and under-ſold themſelves? Do they eſpouſe their Huſbands welfare, or but conſider it in competition with their own eaſe, appetite or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour? What noiſe is heard but the loud Eccho's of their Fortune, with challenge of Equipage and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in their Judgment ſutable, that is, vaſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding it, and ſuch as few Eſtates can ſupport? Is not Home their baniſhment, and <hi>London</hi> indeed their home? If their Lot be not to live in that or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good Town or place of like charge and diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66410:8"/> what exceptions are taken! what objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and delays contrived! The Air is either too moiſt or too cold, too thick or too thin; the ways thereabouts to be ſure are either dirty or ſtony; the Houſe too ſolitary or too near a Street, not of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Fabrick, or modiſh Furniture: The Gentry of thoſe parts not Courtly; not a man it ſhould ſeem within ken qualified for a Gallant; the Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty rude, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Poſſibly they are at length hal'd to their homes as to Priſons, but hir'd, forſooth, with the Donative of a Child's portion or two, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Toys for the Wife, and therewith quiet for the Huſband. Being placed at the Helm of a good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, like a Monkey at the Steerage of a ſhip, their firſt care is to ſolicit acquaintance, and their main buſineſs conſiſts in the Ceremony of receiving and returning viſits; their Entertainments finding work for three or four Servants, their very Salutations and Appointments too for almoſt as many: ſo that here to act the part of good Huſbands in the Vulgar no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both to Wives and Eſtates, to gratifie the one and preſerve the other is perhaps next door to impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            <p>The good Nature of Children ſingly conſidered is of greater moment and advantage than wealth, the improvements of it being far more excellent, and the miſcarriages leſs reparable. For what recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe of Fortune to a Creeple, a diſeaſed Body, an uncomely perſon, above all, a crooked Mind? and what Portion equal to thoſe perſonal Endowments, the propriety whereof neither Fortune nor malice can invade? To this eminent Duty the true Huſwife dedicates her time and pains: her Children are her
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66410:9"/> Garden, her Park, nay her Court. In their tender years her buſineſs is to protect them from diſaſters and injuries, to ſecure their health and growth, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Genius, to inſtruct them in their beſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, yet rather leading than driving them, and ſupplying their defects with her skill and diligence; in all which her thrift is ſutable to her tenderneſs. Her Sons ſhe early reſigns to their Father's Diſcipline, never interrupting it with pernicious fondneſs: In their riper years, ſhe inſenſibly trains them to lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Qualities<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (yet for uſe not oſtentation) her Lectures and Charms chiefly tending to the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of pride and ſloth. Having thus ſeaſoned them with Principles of Thrift and Content, ſhe ſcrapes not for portions, nor is ſolicitous of their preferment, which ſhe truſts may ſucceed to her wiſh, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly it doth; however ſhe acquits and ſatisfies her ſelf with this reaſonable confidence, that if they prove not fortunate, they can ſcarce be miſerable; which yet to our delicate and ſhiftleſs Dames fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently happens. But will our She-gallant now adays admit any ſuch vulgar duty as the tendance of her Children; ſurely, that ſhe leaves for Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks, aſſigning the drudgery thereof to Hirelings, who accordingly perform it to treble Charge and Expence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as needleſs, as fruitleſs: ſhe hears not their complaints or wants, much leſs ſees them, but in their ſad effects, incurable lameneſs or ſickneſs, to the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den expiring even of fruitful Families; no, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of her Dreſſes or Treatments affords not leiſure for ſuch trifles; or if to ſupererogate ſhe mind them by fits, yet through her partiality or uneven Temper, ſuch regard proves worſe than neglect. On
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66410:9"/> her Sons (eſpecially the eldeſt) of courſe ſhe dotes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> underhand fomenting their ſtubbornneſs to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of whatſoever their Father with his Wiſdom builds. In fine, her chief care is to cultivate their pride, the rankeſt Weed of our Nature, by good pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſo induſtriouſly ſubdued: To her own <hi>Idea</hi> ſhe frames them, for indeed better Principles or Manners than ſhe hath how ſhould ſhe infuſe? ſo that people in the Streets ſcarce forbear to proclame them Chips of the old Block; and at laſt in deſpite of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's proviſion, 'tis great odds, they marry either to his diſparagement or their Huſbands undoing.</p>
            <p>The exact ſurvey of their own Eſtates is a skill and employment more worthy of prudent Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords, than ſome other their Entertainments, plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible indeed but not practicable; were it more in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, good Families would not ſo faſt decline. It would impartially diſcover to them their ſtrength or weakneſs, and acquaint them what indeed they have to ſpend; which I dare pronounce is ſeldom half ſo much as Fame and Opinion ſuggeſt unto them: For computing Revenues now adays with their manifold loſſes and Repriſes, they prove in effect like ſome fruits, little more than Shells and Parage; which how generally ſoever diſcours'd, is ſeldom rightly ſtated, ſave by ſuch as have ſmarted for their Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of it. But how harſh a note is this to our Damſels, enured to reckon by thouſands! Can they diſgorge what they have ſo well digeſted, or patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hear, that in the eſtimate of their Huſband's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, there happen'd, forſooth, an unlucky miſtake of Pounds inſtead of Nobles? Alas! that might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the gilding of their next Coach, the reduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66410:10"/> of their Equipage, their forbearance of <hi>London, &amp;c.</hi> No, there's a trick worth two of that, even to ſet the beſt foot forward; not to brook ſuch unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury Truths, but rather to their own and their Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Credit, to admit the popular Cry, and with it conſpire to his Bane.</p>
            <p>Of like neceſſary uſe is it to be vers'd in the Rates and Meaſures of houſhold Expence, which in well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govern'd Families ſhould be almoſt as regular as the victualling of Fleets; to have the faculty of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, but withal provident Houſe-keeping and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment; of procuring Equipage and Furniture of all ſorts at the beſt hand, likewiſe of adjuſting, preſerving and repairing it: for want whereof our Engliſh Ladies are ſaid to have contracted ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy in <hi>Holland,</hi> where by reaſon of the conſtant dearneſs of Proviſions, and endleſs Payments, no man of what Eſtate ſoever without great frugality can thrive or well ſubſiſt, that a Dutch man ſcarce marries one of them without the loſs of his Trading<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit. Some of theſe Qualities the right-bred Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife ſucked in with her Mothers milk, others ſhe learned with her <hi>A B C,</hi> and for the reſt proves no Truant, her Genius being active, and fixed on the <hi>Idea</hi> of Huſwifery as its proper object; wherein her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, if any, are of courſe ſupplied by her Huſbands Experience, whoſe Advice, whether directory or monitory, finds her ear always open to it. But what hope of enammelling a mere Flint? what thought of inſtructing perſons too dull to apprehend of themſelves, too froward to learn? Offer our Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Libertines any Counſel that trenches on their Vanity, or pinches their Sloth, 'tis at beſt <hi>durus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:66410:10"/> and accordingly with them it ſpeeds; reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or contrivance, it ſhould ſeem, are as much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their breeding as Thrift: Rather they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd notes with the good Fellows, whoſe generous Maxime, they ſay, is to drink as long as the Cup will ramn; the utmoſt extent of their Huſband's credit (if they can carry it by hook or by crook) being the only limit of their Expence: otherwiſe Eſtates could not be ſo commonly blown up without noiſe, and as it were with white Powder, nor mouldred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by good, that is, demure and well-meaning Wives, faſter, methinks, than even bad Huſbands diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch them.</p>
            <p>Of Wives adviſedly taken from a frugal Stock, the ſame proof may reſonably be expected as of Trees choſen out of a Nurſery, the Glebe wereof is ſound but barren, and remov'd into a richer Soil; or like a Rheniſh Grape tranſplanted into a Southern Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, the Race whereof is ſaid to be our right Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. Such are commonly unacquainted with deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy or ſloth, and early ſeaſoned with this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, That their eſteem for Virtue and Huſwifery is their beſt Portion: ſo as the improvement of their Condition by Marriage to their Native Qualities, muſt needs add that of Content and Complacence, than which nothing is in Wives more amiable. The Reſtraint of others proves their Manumiſſion, and they are apt to err on the ſafer hand; Retirement: or if their ſprightly Genius with their Youth ſhould incline them to the Gayety of Towns and Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet not being naturalized thereto by Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, they are by the ſenſe of their Duty or perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Engagement without violence reclaimed. Nor
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66410:11"/> is this happy Temper only conſiderable in it ſelf, but in the ſoveraign influence it hath on their Huſbands, thereby often wean'd from their Extravagancies: whereas there is no Purgatory to the unquiet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of ſome Wives, when their boundleſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites or lofty expectations are not gratified. The turbulency of ſuch, if <hi>Solomon</hi> may be credited, turns a Palace into a Cottage, or, if we will truſt Experience, into <hi>Bridewel</hi> or <hi>Bedlam.</hi> Nay though it be but the common Chagrin, and little moods of our peeviſh and affected Dames, the endleſs imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of them too often ſo diſturbs men of better Principles and Humour, that finding themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie ſojourners in their Houſes, under pretence of Civil Inclination, have courted their divertiſement in the freedom of Lodgings at <hi>London,</hi> or welcome of Inns and Taverns which their Purſes command. But then whilſt the Lawleſs freedom of theſe Planets by inviting Courtſhip, if it betray them not, yet ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom fails of expoſing even the beſt of them to their Husband's juſt reſentment, nay to Lampoons and Vulgar Cenſures, with indelible ſtains of Honour; the wiſe and decent Reſervedneſs of theſe fixed Orbs, as it worthily endears them to their Huſbands, ſo it preſerves no leſs their Fame than their Virtue, and perfumes their Memory.</p>
            <p>And as there is nothing more fulſom than the pride of theſe goodly Cyphers at the Spring-tide of proſperity, ſo in any ebb of Fortune, by their droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and whining they at beſt diſcover their droſs. Take from theſe Birds of <hi>Juno</hi> their Train, and is there ought ſo vulgar, indeed ſo deſpicable? But though their Spirits ſink, 'tis great odds their Spleens
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66410:11"/> riſe; and then whether the decay proceed from pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Calamity, private misfortune, or, as too oft it happens, through their own fault, Reaſon and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience give place to Fury and Clamour: the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they brought are aloud objected, and their Huſbands (though indeed the chief, if not the only ſufferers) arraign'd for betraying their innocent wives to the diſtreſs of miſſing their Coaches and Liveries: the noiſe and anguiſh whereof is to ingenuous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſo ſenſible, that it drives them as it were in their own defence to purchaſe their preſent quiet with ruinous compliance and concealment of their Exigencies; it being obſerv'd that our Domeſtick breaches (now ſo familiar) have generally their riſe from the firſt viſible decay of Huſbands in their Eſtates, and their neceſſary abridging the ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch Wives: for they are mere Summer-friends, and a ſort of Legal Concubines; their love depends on their fare, and no Penny, no <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> is their Principle. What a Cordial is this to men in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! ſuch a female Comfort for all the world had <hi>Job.</hi> Much happier is the Omen of generous Matches, Deſert being the womans Dowry: To ſuch the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudes of Fortune are no ſurpriſals. The Virtue of their Education qualifies even their proſperity, and for the moſt part ſecures it: but if the ſame wings of wealth which brought it to them, ſhould carry it from their Husbands, they retreat in order, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily renew their old acquintance with Thrift; nay, with leſs reluctancy can they go, if need be, to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> than moſt Wives are drawn from <hi>London</hi> into ſome neighbouring County; as owning their Husbands welfare for their only intereſt, and that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66410:12"/> for their Country whither his occaſions call them; whoſe very Eclipſe by ſuch chearful aid and compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance proves to him a ſtate rather of Temperance and Retirement than want.</p>
            <p>But laſtly and chiefly, great Portions (as before was hinted) are dearly purchaſed with anſwerable Joyntures to the exceeding detriment of good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, by keeping the Heirs almoſt in perpetual Nonage: whereas by diſpenſing in point of Fortune, all ſuch pretences vaniſh, and moderate proviſions (conſiſtent with the well-being thereof) are chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully embraced; which being accordingly made in in Bar of Dower, and (for the greater ſhare) limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to continue only during Widowhood, are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the beſt, perhaps only ſufficient Fences againſt thoſe fatal Treſpaſſes and Diſſeiſins, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly enſue from the raſhneſs of young wantons in the choice of their ſecond Beds: the Fortune-catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er through his ſilly purchaſe and groundleſs confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, proving in the mean time little better than a Pimp to his ignoble ſucceſſor, and a Butcher to his poſterity, expos'd almoſt as a certain prey to the Intruder. For daily experience acquaints us, that as Widows (ſo continuing, and honourably retaining the name and memory of their firſt Affections) are of all others the moſt faithful and happy Guardians and Executors; ſo there is no hoſtility to the unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalneſs of Mothers, when forſaking as it were their Colours, and betaking themſelves to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe party, they become a kind of Stepdames to their own Brood.</p>
            <p>I foreſee you will meet with ſeveral Objections, commonly urged in excuſe of that ignoble Principle
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66410:12"/> and practice, <hi>viz.</hi> the diſpenſing with any thing in Marriage rather than Money, and compaſſing the Golden Wedge on any terms, which with one of your Judgment muſt even carry little weight: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I ſhall briefly examine the moſt material of them.</p>
            <p>'Tis alledged 1. That theſe Maxims and Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, at leaſt divers of them, are obnoxious to the fair Ladies frowns. 2. If the maintenance of Wives be ſo coſtly as is here ſurmiſed, and if there be ſuch failour or contingency in the Revenue of Land, the greater ſtill the obligation of marrying for Money. 3. By diſpenſing with Portion ſutable to the Eſtate, men incurr the popular Cenſure of being overreach'd in their bargain, and ſo forfeit the eſteem for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. 4. Joyntures anſwerable to the Quality of Husbands, and our Legal rate of Dower ſeem decent if not neceſſary. 5. Settlement of Eſtates upon Marriage hath been ever reputed and found the beſt preſervative of them from being ſquandred by the profuſeneſs, or forfeited by the precipitancy of Youth. 6. Straitneſs of Fortune is generally at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with meanneſs of Education. 7. There are no ſuch Qualities in women as can recompenſe want of Portion, nor any ſuch defects as to counterpoiſe a vaſt Dowry, and therefore thoſe ſurmiſes vain. 8. Such is the Lottery of Marriage through the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes of women, that the whole Advice ſeems fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtical; true worth having no outward Mark. 9. 'Tis confin'd to Gentlemen of great and clear Eſtates who are few, and therefore at beſt of little uſe. 10. Even of ſuch the greatet part marry at an age ſcarce ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of thoſe Counſels, being ſway'd by their amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66410:13"/> inclinations; and whatever caution is uſed in the Bargain, yet by the inſinuation of crafty Wives 'twill be afterwards eaſily defeated. 11. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs even abuſes of ſuch preſcription is a frivolous Enterpriſe, neither will men be ſo dazeled with meer flouriſhes, as not to ſee and purſue their ſolid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</p>
            <p>To the firſt 'tis readily anſwered, That all fair and deſerving Ladies will, I doubt not, take me for their Advocate; and if they ſmile, the frowns of others ſhall the leſs concern me: under that Imperial Banner I aſſure my ſelf both of ſafety and victory.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond I cannot better reply, than by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to the ſeveral <hi>Antitheſes</hi> betwixt Huſwives and Gallants; which, together with the notorious fallacy and encumbrance of great Portions ſtop the mouth of this Objection. To ſay the truth, 'tis with women as with Fire and Water; nothing ſo deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive where they prevail or exceed, nothing ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and uſeful in their proper limits.</p>
            <p>To the third; Men ſhould act with Reaſon, not regarding popular Cenſure, their real welfare being of greater conſequence to them, than the verdict of that incompetent Jury. As to their being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach'd, may not the retaining the Dominion of their Eſtates abundantly ſalve their Credit? Surely they will be ſo far from fearing the Cenſure of wiſe men, as rather to win their applauſe, and perhaps invite their imitation.</p>
            <p>The fourth might better have been urged for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, when Widows were indeed ſuch. But if in moderate and limited Joyntures there be Errour, 'tis at leaſt a ſafe one, reparable at pleaſure, in caſe of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66410:13"/> ſpecial confidence or deſert; the other miſchief in caſe of demerit, being irretrievable: nay, the very reſervation of Power in the Huſband to oblige or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is perhaps the life of his Authority.</p>
            <p>To the fifth, Though no humane Providence be entire and complete; yet the abſolute dependence of eldeſt Sons on their Father's bounty is the likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt means to ſecure their Duty, and curb their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs and Extravagance: however let them at leaſt own their ruine to their own, not their Father's folly; and if periſh they muſt, die rather like men than beaſts, ordained to be innocently ſacrificed.</p>
            <p>The ſixth reflects untowardly on our Gentry, who though diſabled to raiſe Mountains for their Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yet oft-times recompence that want with gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and uſefull Breeding, ſuch as Money perhaps can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not compaſs, and will therefore diſdain that Vulgar ſcandal.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh bids defiance to common Experience, which affords frequent Examples of Wives, by whoſe Huſwifery, without advantage of Dowry, weak and encumbred Eſtates, even in adverſe times, have been notably reſcued and improved: but of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Landlords by hundreds, without any viſible improvidence of their own, ſtrangely undone through the Vanity of women. Nay, there is ſcarce any numerous Brood, which preſents not this variety e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven among Siſters; ſome whereof were born for the ſupport of Huſbands, others for their downfal: ſo conſiderable is that Sex to the Luſtre or Eclipſe of Families. Indeed were Wives but ſo juſt or good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd as to continue their Maiden-thrift in their married State, Huſbands would grow but too rich.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:66410:14"/>
            <p>The eighth reduces the matter to blind Chance, diſabling not only Reaſon but Senſe. Much I allow to the Artifice of Women in appearing to advantage, and with ſuch outſides forbid Minds are affected, like greedy Vermine caught with ſlight Baits; there would not otherwiſe be ſuch Devotions paid to ſuch ſorry Saints: But men of noble Intention are not ſo enchanted; Real worth being to ſuch as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernible from Affectation, as fine Silver from Alchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or true Beauty from Dawbing.</p>
            <p>For the ninth, I admit Gentlemen of entire Eſtates to be herein concern'd, but not excluſively to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all degrees having any ſolid Fund of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue; theſe Maxims being proportionably Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal.</p>
            <p>The tenth is grounded on the preſumption of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable Fondneſs in moſt that marry. Truly I have not of late obſerv'd that amorous humour to be very predominant in our Matches; the other and worſe Extreme of preferring a Licentious Celibate, or marrying with a vicious intent, being, methinks, in far more requeſt. Some there will ever be, in whom Fortune and Folly conſpire to their ruine: Theſe I abandon as Strays and Forfeits to the Lord of the Mannour where they firſt light; but they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively fools. The danger of defeating Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Settlements ſeems yet more remote, there being little fear of ſuch dotage in thoſe Huſbands who had once the Prudence to make them; and leſs encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, one would think, for Wives, by ſuch plain dealing, to proclaim their deſign of Second Marriage.</p>
            <p>The laſt were indeed a juſt Exception, if herein I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66410:14"/> pretended to more than the adviſing my Friend: The ſubject I confeſs is copious enough; one might without ſtraining argue the importance of it to the publick, what price, and conſequently what life it would give to the languiſhing Virtues of Women; what a Curb it would prove, not only to that Sexes Vanity, but to Luxury in general, it being notorious that in effect all our ruinous Pomp may be charged on womens account, as being either by them, or for them incurred. What a ſumptuary Law it would prove, if the extravagance of Wooings and Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings were reduced to their ſimple Decorum; How it would reſtore the Luſtre of our Gentry; how it would check the pride of our Money-monger, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly founded in their greedy ſwallowing of his treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Baits; How it would advance the noble inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Land, by reſcuing it from the ſnare of cheap and proſtitute Encumbrances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But you ſee I trouble not the Policks, leaving our Wits to diſpute, whether the general diſallowing or limiting of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> portions were profitable or practicable: Let others uſe their diſcretion, and take their fortune, you, I dare ſay, are neither Votary nor ſlave to Cuſtom.</p>
            <p>To conclude this tedious Epiſtle, Marry in God's name; your Anceſtors deſerve and require it of you, who both by their Virtue rais'd a Family worthy to be continued, and by their providence left you an Eſtate ſufficient to continue, nay, to enlarge it. Let no licentious Principle of the Age divert, nor Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Prejudice deter you from a ſtate of Life for you ſo expedient; and which for Gentlemen of your condition, (what ever may be ſurmiſed) hath no Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66410:15"/> but of their own forging: Marry, I ſay, but generouſly and circumſpectly, even the moſt worthy or lovely perſon you can meet with or hear of. 'Tis a debt due to your Poſterity that you propagate the beſt you can; nay you owe it moſt of all to your ſelf and your own wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare: if ſomewhat muſt be diſpenſed with (as in all worldly matters there certainly muſt) let it be money, ſince that to my knowledge you leaſt want: but for the propriety of your Eſtate, let nothing wreſt it from you, and ſcorn that all the Bags in <hi>London</hi> ſhould decoy you to ſettle it: reckon it to you as ſacred and eſſential, as to Princes their Militia or Negative Vote; and part no more with it, than, were you a Soveraign, you would be bought or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jol'd tamely to reſign your Sceptre. For matter of Joynture uſe your own Latitude; but limit the main of it to Widowhood, or the Heir's Minority, as you ſee cauſe. Be not ſo ſupine as to make no proviſion againſt Power; above all beware of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Rents: Be Captain of your own Pinnace what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it coſt you; what you loſe in the Hundred, you will abundantly recover in the County; and though you finger not a Token, know 'tis the beſt bargain you will ever drive. For your general and final di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection take that of the Roman Poet, <q>—<hi>Veniunt à Dote Sagittae:</hi>
               </q> With this of the famous Epigrammatiſt,</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:66410:15"/>
               <l>Inferior Matrona ſuo ſit, Priſce, Marito,</l>
               <l>Haud aliter fiunt foemina virque pares.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And thus heartily wiſhing proſperity to your noble Reſolutions, I always continue,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Faithful Kinſman and Servant A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Printed for and Sold by <hi>William Miller.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CRadock's Knowledge and Practice, <hi>Quarto.</hi> His Principles, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Ward,</hi> his two very uſeful and compendious Theological Treatiſes: the firſt ſhewing the nature of Wit, Wiſdom and Folly; the ſecond deſcribing the Nature, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, and Abuſe of the Tongue and Speech, whereby prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally Wiſdom and Folly are expreſſed; wherein alſo are divers Texts of Scripture touching the reſpective heads explained. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fettiplace</hi>'s Chriſtian Monitor, earneſtly and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionately perſwading ſinners unto true and timely Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, by the ſerious view of ſeven weighty Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Complete Bone-ſetter. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66410:16"/>
            <p>The famous Game of Cheſs-play. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shelton's Tachygraphia, Latin. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Emblems, Divine, Moral, Natural and Hiſtorical, expreſſed in Sculpture, and applied to theſe veral Ages, Occaſions and Conditions of man, by a perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A brief Remembrancer, or the right improvement of Chriſt's Birth-day.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Sheet of old Mr. <hi>Dod</hi>'s Sayings, or another Poſie gathered out of Mr. <hi>Dod</hi>'s Garden.</p>
            <p>Hunting for Money, the first part.</p>
            <p>The Hunting-match for Money, the ſecond part.</p>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi>'s Sayings concerning Travellers, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Popiſh and debauched Principles.</p>
            <p>The whole Duty of Man, containing a practical Table of the ten Commandments, wherein the ſins forbidden, and the Duties commanded or implied, are clearly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by famous Mr. <hi>William Perkins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Muſes Fire-works on the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> or the Proteſtant's Remembrancer of the bloody Deſigns of the Papiſts in the never-to-be-forgotten Powder-plot.</p>
            <p>By the ſaid <hi>William Miller</hi> you may be furniſhed with most ſorts of bound or ſtitch'd Books; as Acts of Parliament, Proclamations, Speeches, Declarations, Letters, Orders, Commiſſions, Articles, with other State Matters; likewiſe Books of Divinity, Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Sermons, and most ſorts of Hiſtories, Poetry, Plays and ſuch like; as alſo Tickets for Funerals ready fitted.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:66410:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
